<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The man in the moone, telling strange fortunes, or, The English fortune-teller</title>
            <author>W. M., fl. 1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 721:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The man in the moone, telling strange fortunes, or, The English fortune-teller</title>
                  <author>W. M., fl. 1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. W[indet] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W.M.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-G⁴ H²  (-H2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fortune-telling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:1"/>
            <p>THE MAN IN THE MOONE, Telling STRANGE FORTVNES, <hi>OR</hi> The Engliſh Fortune-teller.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a man flipping through a book.</figDesc>
               <head>Nihil ſub Sole certum.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by I. W. for NATHANIEL BVTTER. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS WORTHIE Friend M. THOMAS SMITH of Clarkenwell, and Gentleman to the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord LISLE, Lord Chamberlane to the Queenes moſt Excellent Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Sir, to rippe vp the excellent parts abiding in you, might be reputed Paraſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call by many, and offenſiue to you, whom I know no whit vaine glorious: to diſcloſe your kindneſle towards my weake deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, would be acounted follie: that I could not receiue a benefit, but make all the world acquainted therewith: to deſire you ſecure this poore infant of my braine with your fauour, as with <hi>Aiax</hi> ſhield were too trite an imitation, an apes tricke: therefore leauing fawning to flatterers, and offence to him that mindes it: bequeathing follie to ſuch, as will not keepe their owne councell and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to them that cannot inuent, I doe plainely preſent this part of my loue vnto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your euer louing <hi>W. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Fortune to you, for the Fortune-tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler meaneth ſo, whatſoeuer you thinke: if his attendant Opinion decipher you plainely, his faſhion is not to make faire figures of deformed bodies: if his Page <hi>Mockſo</hi> gibe at your ill manners, it is to make you mend them, and if hee himſelfe the principall cutteth you to the quicke, know that hee is no cogging Chirurgion: what falſe Orthographie eſcapeth in the print, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to the haſt of the ſuprauiſor of the proofes (for I haue read the ſpelling booke), what blame you put in the penning, lay vpon mee, it will make mee wiſer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:3"/>
            <head>THE MAN IN THE MOONE, TELLING Strange Fortunes. <hi>OR, THE ENGLISH</hi> FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVNE-TELLER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rauelling a long iourney, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one day beyond my reach, the ſudden approach of the night pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented me, ſo that being vnexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in the way, and ſeeing no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creature to direct me, I was affrighted: The ſtarres ſtared vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, beaſts looked wiſtly after me, battes flew about mine eares, and the owle whooted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mine head: no plow-men whiſtling alongſt the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: no ſhepheard ſinging ouer the downes: the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trage was not diſeaſed by the Spaniell: the Hare ſtole his foode without feare of the hue and crie of Hounds and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: whiſtneſſe had taken poſſeſſion of the woods, ſtilnes made aboad in the fieldes, and darkenes domineered in the Zodiacke, no light had I to ſee my footſteps: no voice heard I to make vnto: thus I wandred I knew not where, came to a place, I knew not whether, and had a glimſſe of one ſitting in a porch, I knew not whom. A while I ſtood a
<pb facs="tcp:20674:4"/> looſe, leaning on my ſtaffe like a wearied Pilgrime, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated with myſelfe, whether fortunately, or vnhappily I ſtumbled thither; by the ſollitarineſſe of the houſe I iudged it a Lodge in a Forreſt, but there was no bawling of dogges thereabout; by the multiplicity of barnes, I thought it ſome Farmers tenement, but there was no grunting of ſwine neare it: by the moate about, it ſeemed ſome Gentlemans Mannor, but I could eſpie no Wagges watching, nor wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons wagging out, to breath themſelues when their Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam was couered: what it was, after I had eaten a little heart a graſſe, which grew at my feete, I feared not, and who was the owner, I greatly cared not: but boldly accoſted him, and deſired houſe-roome: he pried in my face, tooke me by the hand, ledde me into his houſe, placed me in a chaire by the fire, and without any intergatories, ſaluted me courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and went into an other roome; ſtrange it was, and ſtruck me in ſome dumpes, but conſidering his gentle action and grauity, I a little reuiued: for he was of yeares many, of ſtature reaſonable, of complexion ſanguine, no pride in his apparell, no ſullenneſſe in his lookes, ſilence ſate in his hall, and ſobriety in his butteries, temperance in his kitchin, and chaſtitie in his chambers, no ſcoulding with his Cookes, nor carrouſing with his Seruingmen: This I obſerued, and ſat very ſadly, till a ſtrip in requeſted me to follow him, where the old man ſat at a table furniſhed, not ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but with ſufficient nouriſhment; downe he bad me ſit and welcome, Grace he ſaid (then thought I, there is no feare in this place, if there be grace) that which ſtood before me I fed on, and dranke when need required: being well refreſhed, as he beganne with thankeſgiuing, ſo he ended ſupper, and then ſaid thus ſoberly vnto me: Sonne you might marueile at your entertainement, and repute mee mute or ſimple to vſe no more words nor circumſtances at my firſt view of you, but it is my faſhion, as they which know me, know. For ſuppoſe I ſhould aſke you, what you are? A ſtranger I
<pb facs="tcp:20674:4"/> know you are, and being a ſtranger vnto me, you may ſay as well what you are not, as what you are: had I demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whence you came or whither you would, for the one you might haue told me a contrary tale, and for the other your ſelfe is vncertaine: from what parentage you are deſcended, I might queſtion you, it is friuolous and womaniſh, if your qualities be degenerate: how you were educated, I might examine you, it is ſuperfluous, your demeanour will informe me: fall to your meate, I might haue bidden you, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if you had a ſtomacke: drinke to you I might; it may be I deſire no further acquaintance of you, till I knowe your conditions further: but howſoeuer if you be my friend, to vſe you vnkindly, were ingratitude: are you mine enemy? to vſe you friendly is charity: if you are capable, you do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my meaning, and ſhall know more ere we part: if you are ignorant, you may taſt part of my mind by the meat drinke and lodging I beſtowe <hi>gratis</hi> vpon you. This is ſhort and ſenſible, thought I, and made him this anſwere in his owne Dialect: Sir, if I could not gratifie your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with louing words, you might deeme me ruſticall: if I ſhould not labour to repay your loue with my kindeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, you might eſteeme mee vnthankefull: but ſeeing I cannot inſtantly performe the one, I will remaine your deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in very deede, and in one word, heartily thanke you for this vnexpected courteſie, and howſoeuer I may ſeeme rude and illiterate, yet was I long trained vp where good manners grew, and learning flouriſhed. I was once my ſelfe a louer of the Muſes too (ſaid hee) but I had a running head, and would take no ſetled courſe, many countries haue I trauelled, and beheld ſundrie manners, but when age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to tame, that neuer otherwiſe ſuppreſſable, <hi>indomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam iuuentutem,</hi> I pent my ſelfe in this houſe, where I haue long time beene reſident: much preferment might I haue mounted to, but I knew it troubleſome, <hi>plus aloes quam mellis habens:</hi> choiſe of wiues I might haue made, but by
<pb facs="tcp:20674:5"/> the triall of others, I perceiued them but <hi>mala neceſſaria,</hi> inconuenient commodities: great riches could I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but I found them fuller of perturbations then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: if I might liue alwaies, perchance then I ſhould make me a Tabernacle vpon earth, but conſidering how ſmall a time I haue allotted in the earth, I reſpected riches as the Sand I trample on, reiected honour as a bubble, a puffe of winde, <hi>vocem populi,</hi> a meere ſound: and weighed women as lightlie as fethers. No my ſonne, that which God hath beſtowed vpon me I am contented withall. If I am now baſe, my griefe is the leſſe: I was neuer better, if I am poore, my ſorrow is the <hi>fuiſſe faelicem,</hi> I was neuerri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: yet haue I that with ſufficeth nature, and this is my greateſt griefe, becauſe I haue ſeparated my ſelfe from the world, and labour to helpe ſuch as want, and wil take paines to come to me, <hi>aut conſolundo aut conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io aut re</hi> I am accounted amongſt the ſilly a cunning man, a South-ſayer, or Diuiner, one that can tell fortunes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Somnia terro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res magicos micacula ſagus Nocturnos le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mures porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Theſſali pideus Hor.</note>Beleeue me ſir (ſaid I) it is ſo bruted here about, and that to morrow many will reſort vnto you, to knowe their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, whereof I was one, not with purpoſe to know my fortune, for I thinke it proper only to the Omnipotent.</p>
            <p>You ſay well, and it is my affliction that they ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that to me which perteineth to my Maker: yet ſince I am conſtrained I will ſhew them their fortunes, and what will betide them euery one: but now ſeeing it waxeth late and you wearie, I referre you to your reſt for this part of the night, and in the morning you ſhall heare more. Kindly we parted, and the next day when I was vp and ready, I found the olde man ſeated in a chaire: who willed me to take my place as a ſpectator.</p>
            <p>He ſat very ſoberly like <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> his beard was reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and his face wrinckled, a plaine gowne girded cloſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his loyues, a paire of blacke buſkins vpon his legges, a fur'd night cap on his head, and a paire of thicke mittens
<pb facs="tcp:20674:5"/> vpon his hands: on his left ſide ſtood a pert <hi>Iuuinall,</hi> as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to giue the welcome to all commers, as a boy in a barre, and as nimble as a paraſite in an old commodie: he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mockſo,</hi> which in mocking ſort deſcribed vnto <hi>Fido</hi> the fantaſticallity of each mans apparell, and apiſhneſſe of geſture, who by their apparell and geſture would giue a ſhrewd gueſſe at their inclinations.</p>
            <p>On the right ſide ſtood another, but of riper yeares, and more ſtayed carriage, yet ſome what criticall and taunting: he Cognominated him <hi>Opinion,</hi> whom he had ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructed in Phiſiognomie, that he would anotonize any ones condition at the firſt ſight, and ſo apparantly diſplay them, that <hi>Fido</hi> his Maſter wou,d tell what would betide them: thus were theſe three addreſſed as actors:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mockſo,</hi> Deſcribed the habite and geſture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opinion,</hi> Reueiled their conditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fido,</hi> Tolde euery man his fortune, as he came vnto him, for the ſame intent: long had they not ſtaied, but one knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the gate, as if he meant to burſt it open: ſee who is there, ſaid <hi>Fido, Mockſo</hi> ſkipped to the doore, giuing euery one the <hi>faelicem aduentum,</hi> and returned, ſaying:</p>
            <div n="drunkard" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The deſcription of the Drunkard comming in a merrie humour to know his Fortune by <hi>Mockſo.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SYr, I may be glad I had neuer a beard, hee would haue ſinged it with his flaming noſe, whatſoeuer he be, hee is troubled with an horſes diſeaſe, the ſtaggers, I thinke your pales anger him, he doth iuſtle them on both ſides: Oake he ſaith they are made of, and ſpitteth whole pottels againſt them; <hi>Eheu quid faciam?</hi> What an hue is his face of? and his teeth as naſtie as if they laie in a graue theſe ſeuen yeres: his cloake will neuer hide his knauerie it is ſo tottered, and his breeches will ſhame all, if he take wide ſtrides: hee hath no hat-band nor girdle, they lie in trouble for two Cannes:
<pb facs="tcp:20674:6"/> now he ſetteth his hat on the toe ſide, and commeth ſailing in like a ſhippe in a tempeſtuous tide.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>The opinion of the Drunkard.</head>
                  <p>THis fellow is one of the faithfull (as they prophanelie terme him) (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) no <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> at meat, but he will drinke many degrées beyond a Dutchman: if you loue him pledge that health, and if you be a good fellow, make no more ſuch ſnuffes: his kingdome is an Alehouſe, and his Scepter a Can, which is ſeldome out of his hand: You queanes or knaues he crieth, no attendance vpon gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen here, though he be but a Tinker: fill vs the other dozen, it is but taking Ludgate one yeare ſooner: then hee flingeth the glaſſes againſt the wals, as if they coſt nothing: and daunceth a round about a Can, as if it were a Maypole: then he doth driuell h s Hoſteſſe, and will dallie with any that weareth a Croſſe-cloth: then hee careth not for a deare yeare, nor to pay his Landlord, but all that hee can get or borrow goeth to the pot: To be briefe with him, hee is his Maſters hinderance, if he be a ſeruant: his ſeruants torment, if he be a Maſter: his wifes croſſe, if he be an huſband: his childrens beggering, if he be a father: his owne ruine, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he is, a deteſted drunkard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido.</hi> The Fortune-tellers Oration to the Drunkard, wherein he telleth him his Fortune.</head>
                  <p>TRue is the Prouerbe, though fuſtie to fine wits, when the drinke is in, the wit is out: but ſeeing you haue ſet a broach the drinke, and drawne out all the dregs too, we may gather the wit is in: the vice you are ſo addicted to, is drunkenneſſe, the mother of
<pb facs="tcp:20674:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> all Miſchiefe, the fewell of Filthineſſe, the roote of Rogeries, the diſtemperance of the Head, the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Senſes, the ſhip-wracke of Honeſtie, the loſſe of time, and voluntarie madneſſe, an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious languor, the deteſtation of manners, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of life: abhorred of God, deteſted of Angels, derided of men. Yet although it be thus horribly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and ridiculous to God, Angels, and men, though it be thus preiudicial to your ſoule, body, and ſubſtance: yet were it a more eaſie matter to drawe <hi>Hercules</hi> his club out of his hand, then to driue you or any of your crew, from this filthie ſinne: but you would turne like the dogge to his vomite, let me or any other perſwade you as we can: and that which cauſeth me to be thus opinioned you are ſo delighted therewith, that you preferre the pleaſure thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other preferment: and now I thinke of it, I remember a prettie tale not impertinent to the ſame purpoſe. A Gentleman of good worth, as he was riding alongſt the high way, mette a ſturdie fellow, who requeſted his almes: the Gentleman replied, that it was ſhame for him to begge, being yong and luſtie, he was able to worke, or fit to ſerue, if he were in apparell: True Sir ſaid the begger, but apparrell is not ſo eaſily gotten, by ſuch a poore man as my ſelfe: goe home with mee ſaid the Gentleman, and I will ſuite thee new, and thou ſhalt waite vpon mee: Sir, aunſwered the begger, I haue a good ſuite of apparell in the next village, which lieth not for aboue eight-pence, if you will helpe me to that firſt, I ſhall thinke my ſelfe beholding vnto you, and will tell you more:
<pb facs="tcp:20674:7"/> the Gentleman rid, as he ledde him: who brought him to an alehouſe, and requeſt him to alight, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him: the Gentleman was contented and ſat downe, expecting when he would call for his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, that he might redeeme it, and take him along with him: the begger called to his Hoſteſſe, ſaying: Hoſteſſe bring hither my Shirt, ſhee brought him a black pot of ale which he drank off: now ſaid he bring me my Dublet, then ſhe brought him another pot of Ale which he dranke off: now my breeches, another pot ſhe brought him, that he dranke off: now bring my hoſe &amp; ſhooes, then ſhe brought him two blacke pots of Ale, thoſe he drank off, now my hat band and cloake, then ſhe brought him three blacke pots of Ale, which he dranke off: when he had done this, he ſaid, Gentleman, this is the ſuite I told you off, and now I haue it, I thinke I am as well apparelled as an Emperour: the Gentleman ſmiling, paied for this ale, and departed: ſo ſome of you might it aduantage them neuer ſo much, will neuer forſake their drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe:<note place="margin">The Dunkards Fortune.</note> this therefore is your fortune you ſhall ſpend all your money and runne ſo long on the ſcore that the very wind pipe of your credite ſhall bee ſo choat, that if you doe not drinke it out with readie pay, your hoſteſſe will kicke you out of her doores: your wife will wiſh you in your graue, your friendes be aſhamed of you, your enemies triumph ouer you: ſober men ſhall ſhunne your companie, boyes laugh at you as you paſſe by them: your bodie ſhall bee ſubiect to diſeaſes: you ſhall liue with neuer a penie in your purſe, neuer a totter on your backe, no man
<pb facs="tcp:20674:7"/> will commit any matter of truſt or ſecreſie vnto you, and in fine you ſhall lie and die in ſome ditch, vnder ſome ſtaule or in ſome priſon: if you like your fortune, proceede as you haue hither too: but if you abandon it, better fortune will betide you: the drunkard began to come prettily well to himſelfe and walked ſomwhat ſoberlie aſide: and then Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo whipped to the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="tobackonist" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Tobackoniſt commeth in a Brauado to the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune-teller: Mockſo deſcribeth him as he approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</head>
                  <p>WHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi> Sir quoth <hi>Mockſo</hi> I know not certainlie, but I thinke he cometh to play you a fitte of mirth, for I behelde pipes in his pockette, Now he draweth forth his Tinder-boxe and his touch-wood, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to his tacklings: ſure his throate is on fire, the ſmoake flyeth ſo faſt from his mouth: bleſſe his beard with a bazen of water leaſt he burne it: ſome terrible thing hee taketh, it maketh him pant and looke pale, and hath an odious taſte, he ſpitteth ſo after it: A Boule and a Broome ſome bodie, if he holdeth on thus long, hee will make a puddle in your porch and keepeth ſuch a ſnuffing and puffing, that he mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all ſmoake againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Tobackoniſt.</head>
                  <p>O Haue patience <hi>Mockſo</hi> (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) he is at his breake-faſt: it is his heauen or rather hell: I ſhould thinke it ſendeth forth ſuch miſtes, fogges, and vapours, fiue Chimnies well fewel'd vent not more ſmoake then his
<pb facs="tcp:20674:8"/> mouth and noſtrils: a man were better haue his houſe ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated between two Brew-houſes, then a but vpon his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: I had rather thruſt my head into a Iakes, then peepe into his chamber. And nothing ſo noiſome were it, to bee yeoman to a cloſe ſtoole, as to continue within fortie foote of his breathing, yet is the cauſer of theſe inconueniences, meat and drinke to him, and he loueth it aboue the loue of women: it is his mornings draught when he riſeth, his conſerues or cates, when he hath well dined, his after noones nuncious, and when he goeth to bedde, his poſſet ſmoaking hote: hee will not walke farre, nor talke long without it: nay he will looſe his victuals rather then neglect it: pawne his hat band but he will haue it. To be breefe with him, he is his owne ſtrengths enféebler, his beauties blemiſher, his wittes blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his memories decayer, and his appetites abater. A toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Tobackoniſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>The Oration of <hi>Fido</hi> to the Tobackonist, ſhewing his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</head>
                  <p>SIr, ſaid <hi>Fido,</hi> if I ſhould extract the beſt counſell I could, being diſſwaſiue from your Tobacko-tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you would take it in ſnuffe, cuſtome hath ſo ſtrongly combined you therunto, that it were too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble a knot for me to vntye: yet this let me tell you, that it is as an incenſed <hi>Atropos</hi> to a long life, clipping off the thred before it be thoroughly ſpun, decaying and drying vp the prolonger of breath: but you are perſwaded, as others few, that it doth procure the contrary: you thinke it a medicine for euery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie; giue you Tobacko, and a figge for the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: ſay it were Phyſicke, as you affirme, yet Phyſicke is not taken at al times and ſeaſons, continually with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:20674:8"/> 
                     <hi>Interim:</hi> neither is one kind of Phyſicke admin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to all bodies, conſtitutions, and diſeaſes: but Tobacko may bee compared to the potion which <hi>Circe</hi> gaue to <hi>Vliſſes</hi> ſouldiers, metamorphoſing them into ſwine: ſo this pretious weede, as you eſteeme it, doth ſo ſelfe-beſot thoſe which take it, that like ſwine they wallow in the myre of their admiring conceits: that neither reaſon can rule them, nor experience of others harmes ſuſtained thereby, make them refraine. I will not denie, that conceit may worke wonders: but thoſe wonders are onely in conceite, as I haue heard of ſome, who through an irreformable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, haue imagined their noſes to be as bigge as Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, to flye in the ayre, contend and quell Diuels by their owne naturall ſtrength: ſo you, only by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, thinke richly of the operation of your Indian Pudding, hauing contrarie qualities in it, a thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Philoſophy, and working miraculous matters, a quillit aboue nature: as if you be fat, then you take it to make you leane, (againſt the walles I hope you meane) if leane, then it will make you fat, put <hi>V.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> to fat and I will beleeue you: if dull, quicke witted: if obliuious, reuiue your memories, doing theſe things and many more; and helping all manner of diſeaſes, the poxe it will as ſoone. But I could eaſily refute theſe, and all your opinions, had not this text beene thoroughly trauer'ſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with great iudgement and learning,<note place="margin">Didimus wrote ten thouſand bookes of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Agrip. de vani. Scien.</note> in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne diſputation; and in the booke, entituled, <hi>Worke for a Chimnie ſweeper:</hi> and were there as many vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnes written concerning this ſubiect, as <hi>Didimus</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20674:9"/> wrote of the Grammer, you would martyre them, leafe by leafe, and light your pipes at the flame: <hi>Niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in vetitum,</hi> that which wiſedome doth forbid folly will follow. This therefore is your Fortune, if you leaue not taking your Indian ſtuffe betime, cuſtome will ſo confirme you to it,<note place="margin">Vincere conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem dura eſt pugna.</note> that when you perceiue the inconueniences, and feele the folly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you cannot forſake it, though you will: you ſhall die before your date: your body ſhall be in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſundrie ſickneſſe, and ſo ſooted with the ſmoake thereof, that it will be as foule as hell, ſending forth ſuch a filthy ſent, that your breath will bee death to your wife, or any that ſent it, but ſuch as your ſelfe: Aſide the Tobackoniſt ſtepped, and another knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="prodigall" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Prodigall commeth ſtalking in, to know his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, <hi>Mockso</hi> decyphering his apparrell and gate.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mockſo</hi> anſwered: Sir I know not of what Countrey, Nation, Sex or faſhion he is, his face is like a mans: but by the tone ſide of his head like a woman: ſome purblinde Barber powled him, to cut his haire ſo vnequally, and leaue one locke a quarter of a yard longer then the other: by the blocke of his head (put them both together, and ſee what they ſpell) he ſhould bee a Spaniard, but his dublet ſheweth him a Frenchman: now I ſée his breeches made like a paire of Smiths Bellowes, erected with the ſmall end vpwards: he ſeemeth a Walloone: marrie there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in his cloake, he tooke the length thereof by the old apes of Paris Garden: a ſweete youth no doubt, for he hath two
<pb facs="tcp:20674:9"/> Roſes on his ſhoes, to qualifie the heat of his feete: he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very bigly, and commeth prauncing in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Prodigall.</head>
                  <p>THis Prauncer (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) hath beene a wilde colt, and leaped thorough many honeſt mens gates in his dayes: he was his fathers dotage, and his mothers darling; he hath ſpent more vpon his paunch then the Primate of Belly gods: guſted downe his throate more then <hi>Cleopatra</hi> quaffed in a Brauado to <hi>Marke Anthonie:</hi> layed more gold vpon his backe, then that which procured paſſage for the Aſſe into the Caſtle would defray: naturall meat will not ſuffice him, he feedeth artificially: natiue apparell will not content him, he flieth for vplandiſh faſhions: honeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie is not for his loines, hee watcheth nightly, and walketh by day, to entrappe other mens wiues: he is neuer ſafe, but when he is in peſtilent companie: neuer well, but when he is euill employed, Whores he ſupporteth, Vintners he aduanceth, Tailers he maketh Gentlemen, if he be not too farre in their bookes: to be briefe, he is Lecheries <hi>Maece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> idleneſſe patrone, Prides founder, Gluttonies erector, Drunkenneſſe good god-father: an impudent Prodigall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>The Fortune-tellers Oration to the Prodigall, declaring the inconueniences of diſſolute liuing, and his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</head>
                  <p>SIr, you are generouſly deſcended,<note place="margin">Diuitiae, par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, amici, &amp;c. ſunt vt illius ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus qui ea poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidet, qui vti ſcit, ei bona, qui non recte vtitur ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</note> the greater is your ſhame, to expoſe your ſelfe to an ignoble courſe of liuing: much riches were you bequeathed, the more is the pittie, you haue ſo little grace to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>employ them, well are you featured, it is ill beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:20674:10"/> vnleſſe you would preſerue your beautie better: for that which GOD and nature haue ordeined for your good, by your ill vſing, you turne to your owne ouerthrowe: had your progenitors runne the race you doe, they had neuer wonne the Golden ball, which made you a Gentleman: you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it an eminence, to be rarely arrayed: others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe, are not ſo conceited: you ſuppoſe it a great glory to laſh your coyne, you care not where, nor vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon whom; though they will aduance you, which receiue benefite thereby, yet ſuch as will not profite themſelues by ſuch meanes, reſemble you to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which waſteth it ſelfe to giue other light: you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it an extraordinarie happineſſe to be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with many and ſundry beauties, you ſhall feele the contrarie, pride will procure your fall, when you wot not of it: exceſſe deuoure your riches, ere you are aware: variety decay your bodie, when you think it doth moſt delight it: and when your bodie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, your wealth deuoured, your ſelfe fallen, goe to your Goſſips, which now will hang like goodly ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels about your necke, and come with your purſe emptie: <hi>ſtabis Homere foras,</hi> you may ſtand like an impecunious Whore-maſter at their doores: come to your Tradſemen, which now cappe and cringe you, and ſee if you ſhall receiue any further comfort, then monefull words, Alaſſe, it is pittie, would wee were able (good wiſhes for themſelues:) and laſt of al, frequent the Ordinaries, which you haue in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enriched, and marke how they will moane their own miſchances, how they ſit at an vnmerciful rent:
<pb facs="tcp:20674:10"/> what loſſes they haue ſuſteined by pilfering; how many haue runne away in their debts, and a thouſand ſuch circumſtances, which you neuer heard, nor are likely, ſo long as you haue money or meanes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Dum iuuet &amp; ridet vultu fortuna ſereno,</l>
                     <l>Indelibatas cuncta ſequuntur opes:</l>
                     <l>At ſimul intonuit, fugiunt nec noſcitur vlli,</l>
                     <l>Agminibus comitum qui modo cinctus erat.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Whilſt you are mounted on the throne of fortune, great men will countenance you, Gallants be your aſſociates, Paraſites flatter you, Brokers borrow for you, Vſurers lend you, Citizens cap you, Lawyers plead for you, Seruingmen crouch to you, Wantons hang like Burres vpon you: but when you are deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnder the wheele of chance, great men will not greatly regard you, Gallants hoiſt their toppes and toppe Gallants, and ſaile from you, Flatterers ſhun you, Brokers will not brooke you, Vſurers vſe you rigorouſly, Tradſemen treade on the to ſide of the way, Lawyers leaue you, Seruingmen hang the head as they meete you, Wantons wiſh or worke your ouerthrowe. This therefore is your Fortune, If you proceede as you haue begunne, your full feeding wil make you leane, your drinking too many healthes will take all health from you, your leaping the pale will cauſe you looke pale, your too cloſe following the faſhion, will bring you out of all forme and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, your careleſſe life will lead you to a miſerable death: yet you may preuent your misfortunes, if now you will take opportunity: you haue ſome wealth left, husband it carefully: of a little well ordered will
<pb facs="tcp:20674:11"/> riſe more profite, then much careleſly diſpoſed: yet your wit is pregnant, by induſtrie you may ſeaſon it with wiſedome: yet your bodie is not paſt cure, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred diſeaſes are ſoone remedied: if you ſcoffe at me for my good will, you may repent when you lie like a nutmegge in a grate, or ride poſt with a hempen halter out of the world: but if you accept it, much good may it doe you.</p>
                  <p>The Gallant very penſiuely walked aſide, and <hi>Mockſo</hi> went to the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="servingman" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Seruingman waiting on this Gallant, commeth in to know his Fortune, whom <hi>Mockso</hi> decyphereth.</head>
                  <p>Who is it, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A moſt courteous creature, anſwered <hi>Mockſo,</hi> So, ſtroke vp your fore-toppe in any caſe; piſh, your band hangeth right enough: what? yet more creuiſes in your ſtockings: fie vpon it, how complementall he is, and kiſſeth his hand as if he were in loue with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Seruingman.</head>
                  <p>THis fellow (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) though he be no drunkard, yet he is none of his owne man, he was a pretty boy, an handſome ſtripling, and is a proper man, peeuiſh in his childhood, proude in his youth, prodigall now in his beſt yeares: he ſpendeth his portion in hope of preſerment, waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſubſtance in liewe of aduancement, conſumeth quite all in expectation of ſome requitall; his greateſt felicity is to court the Chamber maides in a corner, and his chiefeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe to make his Maſters friends dependants drunke; bee fawneth vpon them his Maſter fauoureth, and frumpeth
<pb facs="tcp:20674:11"/> thoſe his Miſtreſſe frownes on: he was trained vp in ſome point of a Ioyners trade to make legges, and the beſt part of his Rhetoricke is I forſooth, and no forſooth: the iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he ſtandeth bound too, is to runne at all calles, riſe at all houres, and ride in all ſeaſons: eating that which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter left, and wearing that which his Maſter left, if hee can get it: which ſheweth that he is the Ante-ambulo of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle woman, the conſequent of a Gentleman, the antecedent of a Port-mantua or a Cloke-bagge: A Seruingman.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fidoes</hi> Oration to the Seruingman, teaching him briefely how to behaue himſelfe in ſeruice, and telling him his Fortune.</head>
                  <p>INgratefull and hard hearted are many of our age, reſpecting none but ſuch as profite and pleaſure them at the inſtant: induſtrious therefore ought you be, to get your Maſters fauour, and hauing gotten it, circumſpect to keepe the ſame: and albeit ſome there are, reſpecting their ſeruices no longer then they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie their luſtes and lucre, thruſting them out of their gates vnrewarded for the ſmalleſt trifle and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, conceiued againſt them; yet the world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and thouſands will acknowledge the fluent libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of true bred Gentillity, extended to their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers: who by the raiſing hand of their Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, haue aſcended many high and loftie ſteppes of dignity: but ſuch Maſters are not ſowne euerie where, neither were they ſwaggering drunkards, or ſwearing Iackes, which haue thus flouriſhingly
<pb facs="tcp:20674:12"/> ſprowted vp by ſeruice: but men of good demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and well quallified: for the wiſe looke not only on the out ſides, they prie into behauiour, integritie and vprightneſſe: It is not profound quaffing or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering will doe you any good, royſting and ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wil neuer raiſe you (vnleſſe vp to the Gallowes.) This therefore is your fortune, If you be in good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and will not with care and diligence keepe you in it, when you would haue the like againe, you ſhall goe without it: if you take time you may thriue, but if you let him paſſe by, you may call your heart out, and neuer reclaime him: for time though hee be an olde man, yet he is quicke of foote, and hauing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſtart of any, is neuer ouer-taken: if you gather nothing in the Summer of your youth, in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your age you may goe begge: for hee that might doe well and would not, when hee wanteth ſhalbe vnpittied, and when you become old &amp; poore too, then ſhall you be ſpurned with the heele of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine by euery foote-boy: reiected as an old woman which ſpent her youth wantonly, then ſhall you heare of your olde vagaries, your former follies ſhal be laide in your diſh: if in your iollity you wronged any, they will wait for reuenge in the time of your want and weakeneſſe: when the Lion was olde and toothleſſe, the Aſſe reuenged an inueterate iniurie he had ſuſtained long before, but now you are in place, if you demeane your ſelfe honeſtly: now you are young preſerue that you get carefully: now you are in ſeruice, performe it faithfully: you may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after purchaſe much comfort, goods and credit. So
<pb facs="tcp:20674:12"/> the creature followed his Maſter, and another knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="lewde woman" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The lewde woman commeth to knowe her Fortune, whom <hi>Mockso</hi> deſcribeth entring.</head>
                  <p>WHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One with a maſke forſooth, becauſe you may aſke, (ſaid <hi>Mockſo</hi>) a woman of tall ſtature and vpright bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (it is wel if her life be like it) high forehead round cheeks, dimpled chinne, ſleeke necke, and ſlender waſte, in a light co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured hat, light coloured fanne, light coloured gown, though ſhe were in the darke, ſhe would appeare a light woman.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion anatomizing the conditions of the wicked Woman.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> (Said <hi>Opinion</hi>) this is one of your lazie liquerous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciuious feminine ingenderers, more wauering then a Wethercocke, more wanton thenan Ape, more wicked then an Infidell, the very ſinke of ſenſuality, and poole of putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: a <hi>Sylla</hi> to Citizens, and <hi>Caribdis</hi> to Countrie men: a comfort for cut-purſes, and a companion for conycatchers: a Factor for many Tauerns, and Benefactor for moſt Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Surgeons: a palſie to the bodie, a canker to the ſoule, a conſumption to the purſe: by birth commonly a Baſtard, by nature a Camball, by art a puritan: in aluring a Syren, in ſhew a Saint, in deede a Diuell; and in plaine Engliſh, a Whoore: of all iniquities beleeue her not, for ſhee liueth by lying: touch her not, for ſhe is pitch, <hi>inquinans omnes qui tangunt eam:</hi> proffer her nothing, for ſhe wil pocke eat al. And now ſir ſhee appeareth in her lightneſſe before you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20674:13"/>
                  <head>The Fortune-tellers Oration to the Mercinarie wicked woman, declaring the abomination of her life and fortune.</head>
                  <p>FAire creature, as I haue beene effectually infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of your conditions: ſo would I labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them: but I might with as great hopes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make a black More white, as to change your minde, and eaſier raiſe an olde Oake from the earth with my decrepit ſhoulders, then roote out that luſt which hath ſo long time beene ſet in your heart: yet if you would conſider the inconueniences thereof, which are, to effeminate the minde, weaken the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, endanger the ſoule, it might proue a motiue to diſſwade: you would account your ſelfe madd, if kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing poiſon to be blended in a lumpe of ſuger: you ſhould for the ſweetneſſe of the ſuger, ſwallowe the poyſon: what then can you make now of your ſelfe, knowing luſt a pleaſant poyſon, hindering your health, ingendering diſeaſes, bringing age before his time, blemiſhing your beauty, ere it be out of the bloſſome, dulling your wit before it be well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and drawing your minde from all vertuous co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, this you know for certainty, yet you will liue in ſenſuality diſdaining <hi>Diana,</hi> and be a votarie to <hi>Venus:</hi> contemning <hi>Vesta,</hi> and deuoting your ſelfe to quotidiall daliance: making a mock at marriage, you will not enter into the bondes thereof, becauſe you will liue looſely, without controll or ſubiection of
<pb facs="tcp:20674:13"/> an husband: yet are you ſeruile to all ſlauerie, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the controlement of euery ſwaggerer: he that hath money may command you: he that can domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere will inſult ouer you, making you crouch and curuet when he pleaſeth: but if no warning wil make you wiſe, this then will be your fortune: You ſhall be ferrited like a Cony out of euery burrow, baited like a Beare, whipped like a Iade, long ſhall you not dare to abide in one place, Authority will ſo cloſely purſue you: what you get in a quarter, you ſhall ſpend in a moneth: nothing that you get will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper with you: and what beauty &amp; delectation your body now containeth, ſhall be of ſmall continuance, your haire which now is faſt and thick, ſhall fall from your head like leaues in Autumne: your forehead which now is ſmooth, ſhall ſoone be wrinkled like parched parchment: your complexion which now is ſanguine, ſhall be of a ſaffron colour, your cheekes thinne, your noſethrils putrifactions, your mouth toothleſſe, your breath noyſome, your fleſh rotten, your bones cankerous, your pleaſure ſhall be turned into paine, your ſinging into ſorrow: Aches ſhall lodge in your head, anguiſh in your heart, diſeaſes in euery part &amp; parcell of your body: and after all theſe, thy ſoule ſuffer perpetuall torments. A ſide ſhe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and <hi>Mockſo</hi> without any knocking, skipped to the doore, for the Wagge imagined, ſhee could not want companions or ſeruants in this age, ſo long as her good face laſted.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="retainer" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20674:14"/>
                  <head>The retainer, which waited on the woman, entereth to know his fortune, whom <hi>Mockſo</hi> deſcribeth as hee enters.</head>
                  <p>IS there any other come (ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi>) There is one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, anſwered <hi>Mockſo,</hi> he will ſcarce ſée the way in, his haire hangeth ſo in his light: <hi>Fatuus in facie, &amp; leno in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> He looketh fat in the face, and leane in the body: how full of choler he is? yet ſo long as thoſe huge flops ſwagge about him, he will be in ſome compaſſe: his bootes are wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled, as though they were made of olde wiues faces: what capt on the toes? ſure he will not put off one of thoſe caps to the beſt man that méeteth him, &amp; in ſober ſadneſſe his ſpurres haue ſcaped a ſcouring, they looke ſo ruſtily, whatſoeuer he be, I thinke he would proue an honeſt man, if hee would waſh his face and ſerue God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion vpon the retainer.</head>
                  <p>SErue God (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) the diuell he will as ſoone, hee hath not ſéene the inſides of a Church theſe ſeuen yeares, vnleſſe with deuotion to pick a pocket, or peruert ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt mans wife, he would on purpoſe be pued with all: vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie is his contemplation, ribaldrie his talke, and deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his déedes, Cardes are his darlings, wherewith he play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and a paire of Dice his onely Paradice: he will omit no villanie, he can cleanly commit, he will cheat his father, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen his mother, and cony-catch his owne ſiſter, if he can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the meanes how: his owne wife he will make a proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute for mony, and hold the candle to any incarnate diuell, whilſt he committeth the déedes of darkneſſe with her, ſixe pence will make him ſweare or forſweare any thing: in a word, he is a Poſt for Puncks, an Harbinger for Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers,
<pb facs="tcp:20674:14"/> a Blood-hound for Bawdes: a perfidious Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his ſpeech to the Pander, ſhewing his lewdneſſe and fortune.</head>
                  <p>O Lamentable, thy caſe is damnable, thy trade odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, thy ſelfe abominable, thou art a man whoſe conditions I know not by experience, neither haue I reade of many ſuch as thy ſelfe in auncient Writers, yet ſome of thy ſect there were, of whom I tooke lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle notice, becauſe I neuer meant to haue any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with them: notwithſtanding, ſeeing I haue heard ſo much, I could amply delate of thy ſinne, but I know it needleſſe, for my hope is, I haue deiected the foundation, whereon all thy practiſes are built, I meane the woman thy Miſtreſſe, which was euen now with me, and if ſhee fall from her former follie, thou canſt not ſtand, vnleſſe thou getteſt ſome croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked prop to ſupport thee, which cannot hold long: expect therefore no other fortune, then vntimely death, either by the ſtab in ſome drunken fray, mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the defence of your maintainer, or by ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe got by her, or by the halter, if you doe not alter: away the Pander walked after his Miſtreſſe, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knocked at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="extortioner" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The extortioner hobleth to know his fortune, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Mockſo,</hi> as he entereth.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido,</hi> that commeth next? <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, vietus, veternoſus ſenex:</hi> a wiſe man Ile
<pb facs="tcp:20674:15"/> warrant him, for he can kéepe him ſelfe warme: no friend to the Barber it ſhould ſéeme, by his ruſticall, ouer growne and vnfinified beard: his gowne is throughly foxt, yet he is ſober, for hee looketh as though he quenched his thirſt with whay and water, rather then with wine and ſtout Béere, and his Mandilion edged round about with the ſtigmaticall Latine word <hi>Fur;</hi> a ruffe about his neck, not like a Ruffian but inch broad, with ſmall ſets, as if a péece of a Tobacco pipe had béene his poking ſtick, his gloues are thruſt vnder his girdle, that you may ſée how he rings his fingers: bleſſe his worſhip, now he commeth coughing in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Extortioner comming to know his fortune.</head>
                  <p>HE is (ſaid <hi>Opinion) miſer qui nummos admiratur,</hi> miſerable or an able miſer, which maketh much of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Gold is his God, and Siluer his Saint, Bondes are his Bibles, and Obligations his Horizons, Scriueners are his Prieſts, which doe his ſeruice, and conſoning Brokers his Chriſtian brethren. Security is his ſecretarie, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants his ſeruing men: he liueth by vſe, like a Bawde, and dealeth deceitfully, like a cheating gameſter: he is a rare Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimiſt, which from a little gold and ſiluer wil abſtract a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in time: Better is a poore Gentleman to fall into the pawes of a Lion, then betweene his clutches, and may with more ſafety eſcape the gripe of a ſhe Beare, then to be relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from his leaſes: to be briefe with him: he is an inſatiable cormorant, or rather corne-vorant, a bottomleſſe Bara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrum, a mercileſſe mony-monger, a filthy forty in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, an vnconſcionable Extortioner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20674:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his Oration to the Extortioner, diſplaying his dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable dealing, and Fortune.</head>
                  <p>FAther, you are welcome, and without feare or flatterie, I will breefely tell you my minde: You haue long traffickt in a wicked and vnlawfull trade, wicked I call it, becauſe it is repugnant to the lawes of the higheſt enacter of all decrees: vnlawfull I may auouch it, becauſe I neuer knew nor heard of any good law maintaining it: for the former, if you run ouer the booke of bookes, you ſhall finde many fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements denounced againſt you, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you cannot contradict it by no Countrie lawes, which although they flatly denie thee, to take aboue tenne in the hundreth, a veniall ſinne in reſpect of thy capitall and deadly offence: yet dooth it not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe thee to take ſo much, but taxeth thee if thou vſurpeſt any more. But what ſhould I talke of this text, which hath beene throughly intreated of by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more iudicious then my ſelfe? or why ſhould I waſt my breath to thee, which haſt neither faith, hope nor charity? What doe I talke of theſe thinges to thee, whom the loue of riches hath ſo beſotted, that it is impoſſible to diuert it? or how ſhould I thinke to preuaile by diſſwading: <hi>Cum te ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ferui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus aestus Dimoueat lucro, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> hyemps, ignis, mare, ferru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> when neither the parching heate, nor benumbing cold; neither fire, ſword, nor ſea, can diſſwade:
<q>
                        <l>Impulit amentes, auri<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cupidine caecos,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:20674:16"/>
                        <l>Ire ſuper gladios, ſuper at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cadauera patrum.</l>
                     </q> Therfore if your future fortune (That is,<note place="margin">Quis pauper? a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarus Auſon. Semperinops qui cun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cupit. Clau.</note> that which ſhall light vpon you hereafter, will not drawe you from your daily practiſing the ſame, nothing will) which is this: You ſhall alwaies want, though you haue neuer ſo much, <hi>ſemper auarus eget, Hor.</hi> though thou art a Maſter, thou ſhalt be alwaies a ſeruant, moyling for a mite, and watching to ſaue a pennie; thou ſhalt liue in perpetuall terrour and feare, ſhee that lyeth in thy boſome ſhall make thee ſuſpitious, leaſt ſhe ſteale from thee; they which were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of thine owne bodie, will ſcarre thee, leaſt they robbe thee: all that looke neere the place, where thy gold lyeth, thou wilt be iealous of, leaſt they lurke to defeate thee of it: <hi>Non vxor ſaluum te vult, non filius, omnes Vicini oderunt noti pu eri at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> puellae:</hi> thy wife will wiſh the hanged, thou keepeſt her ſo barely; thy children pray for thine end, thou maintaineſt them ſo baſely; thy neighbours and kinsfolkes ſpeake broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thee, thou vſeſt them ſo cruelly; and when thou art dead, Diuels hurry thee to perdition, wiſhes damne thee to euerlaſting torments, and curſſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort with thy funerall: Nay thy wife ſhall be enamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſome ſpend-all, which ſhall waſt all as licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as thou haſt heaped together laboriouſly: thy children neuer thriue with ought thou diddeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath them, it was ſo vilely gotten, and thy name ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vtterly blotted out, or remaine infamous to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. If you like your fortune proceed, but if you miſlike it, deſiſt from your racking and rayſing, your powling and pinching the poore: recompence
<pb facs="tcp:20674:16"/> them which you haue wronged, or at the leaſt, iniury none no more, but doe good according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of your goods, and ſo you may bring a bleſſing to your ſelfe and poſterity. The Extortioner walked aſide, and another knocked at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="glutton" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Glutton entreth to know his fortune, whom <hi>Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> decyphereth.</head>
                  <p>WHo is next, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monſtrum horrendum informe ingens,</hi> A monſtrous man (ſaid <hi>Mockſo</hi>) your gate is too little for this Grecian horſe, if you cauſe not part of your wall to be plucked downe, he cannot come in: God bee thanked, hee hath the witte yet, to enter f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eling, like a Gentlewoman with an huge Farthingall: how he puffeth and bloweth like a ſhort winded Hackney: now he approacheth wallowing like a woman with childe: he might be an Oxe for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oule, a Bull for his necke, a Cow for his belly, and a Calfe for his wit, I make no queſtion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Glutton.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOna verba Mockſo,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) he will hate you to death if he heare you and worke you a michiefe if you miſuſe him, he is a great man, I can tell you, and in huge requeſt amongſt no ſmall fooles: <hi>Phago</hi> might be his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, for his full feeding, and <hi>Garagantua</hi> his Sire, for his gormand zing: he is none of your ordinarie fellowes, which will ſuffice nature for three pence, giue him an Oxe roſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d whith a pudding in his belly, a Rabbit is but a bitte with him, and he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ranch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apons as faſt as a begger wil cracke Lice. he is a tall man at a table, and will toſſe a pike
<pb facs="tcp:20674:17"/> ſtrenuouſly, if it be ſoaked in white-broth: he is none of your great talkers, but will do prettie well at a dinner: if ſilence be a vertue, he is a vertuous Gentleman, for at meate hee cannot entend to talke for eating, and betweene meales, hee ſleepeth ſoundly: to be briefe with him, he is a peſtilence to Paſties, which ſweepeth many of them ſheere away, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to capons, Chick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns, and other poultry, a ſepulchre to Seafiſh, and others in ponds, moates, and Riuers, a ſharp ſheepe-biter, and a marueilous Mutten-monger, a gorbelly Glutton.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his Oration to the Glutton, inueying against his ſinne, and reuealing his fortune.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TAntum cibi &amp; potionis adhibendum eſt, vt refici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur vires, non vt opprimantur:</hi> Sir, I ſalute you with this ſaying of <hi>Cicero,</hi> becauſe I perceiue you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ballace your belly, an vngratefull member, neuer thankefully repaying that which is done vnto it, but daily calling for more then is needefull; and why ſhould man that hath vnderſtanding to iudge, and reaſon to rule, be ſo ſeruile to filthy appetite? a ſmall thing will content nature, and ſatiety doth rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe then pleaſure her: it maketh her vnfitte to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any agill or actiue thing: beſide the ouerplus might tend to many profitable vſes, but you cannot fall too vnleſſe your table bee fully furniſhed: how did they in the old time, when they were ſufficed with ſuch ſuſtenance as the Graſſe and trees afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they liued longer, and were ſtronger then they of this inſtant; they had no Cookes to prouide them
<pb facs="tcp:20674:17"/> cates, hunger was their beſt ſawce, labour and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Cookes, which compoſed that ſawce, if you would feed with the like ſawce, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſed by the ſame Cookes, it would take you a button lower, and cauſe you looke not like <hi>Boreas;</hi> as you now doe: if not, I cannot remedie it, neither will I ſpeake to your deafe god Bell, or rather bellie anie longer: your fortune will be this: manie diſeaſes wil be ingendered in you, through your immoderat eating: fit for no Countrie ſeruice will you be, neither in martiall, nor domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call affaires, a foole ſhall you liue, and a dunce ſhall you die, &amp; that ſooner too then otherwiſe you wold, keeping a ſparing and temperate diet: all the pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of your paunch ſhall be to no other purpoſe, for you ſtriue for all delicate creatures to feed your ſelfe, and you your ſelfe ſhall be food for the wormes. A way the glutton lagged, and <hi>Mockſo</hi> highed to the doore, expecting that as he was larded, ſo hee would be garded with ſome or other: for rich men haue manie friends, and neede not walke alone vnleſſe they pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="parasite" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Paraſite aſſociating the glutton to the gate, ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Mockso</hi> deſcribing him.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is that (ſaid <hi>Fido</hi>)? a finicall fellow, anſwered <hi>Mockſo,</hi> as full of ſalutations as a Fidler, his Hat was off before I could aſke him what he would, and his knee licked the ſuperficies of your threſhold, ere I bad him enter, a crafty fellow, I feare, he is ſo full of courteſie, and ſome couſoning companion, he hath ſuch a flearing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:
<pb facs="tcp:20674:18"/> now he eieth you ſir, his head is bare, O rare, what an excellent dumb ſhew is this? thriſe hath he kiſſed his hand and made you three lowe congies in comming three ſtrides: now he approacheth neere you, I think he meaneth to make a Pope of you, and kiſſe your toes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Paraſite.</head>
                  <p>HE is none of your Cynicks, nor Criticks, hee is no <hi>Momus</hi> that ſnappeth Vice by the ſhinnes, as ſhee paſſeth by him: hee reſpecteth not what men be, ſo they be rich, he wil liue, when they lack: he fleareth not in your face for nothing, nor reflects his legges without ſome ſurmiſed reaſon, he will fawne on you like a Spaniell, follow you like a foiſting Hound for his commodity, ſay what you wil, hee will ſweare to it, doe what you delight in, hee wil encourage you: are you adicted to drink drunke, he wil gibe at ſobriety, and chriſten her with innumerable nick-names. Doe you loue whores? he wil ſcratch where it itcheth not, and tickle your eares with a tale of variable venerie: haue you one ſparke of goodneſſe? he wil extoll you aboue meaſure; haue you neuer ſo much ill? he wil mitigate it: he is in Tantolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies of praiſing, that you like, and extreame in diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that you doe condemne, be it neuer ſo praiſe-worthie: he giueth nothing his due or proper right, but either too much or to little, he careth not for the meane: he wil peruert anie thing for his purpoſe: if you be a coward, hee ſaieth you are wiſe and trulie valerous: if prodigall, then generouſlie libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: are you a niggard? then frugall and prouident: is your head great, a note of policie: is it little, the loftieſt men are ſo marked: is your noſe long, an excellent ornament: hee knew a great Ladie that neuer commended other: is it ſhort, it is the comlieſt: are you high coloured? it is the ſoundeſt complexion: are you pale? it is amorous and attractiue: are you tall? all that are lower then you, are dwarfes: are you low? all that are taller, are lubbers or May-poles: to bee
<pb facs="tcp:20674:18"/> briefe with him: he wil ſoothe you vp in anie ſinne, hugge anie hainous humor in you foſter anie follie, wealthie mens wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſher, pouerties deadlie enemie, a falſe hearted fawning Paraſite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his Oration to the Paraſite, reuealing his faults and fortune.</head>
                  <p>Sir (ſaid <hi>Fido</hi>) ſince your diſpoſition is ſo largelie deſcribed, I ſhall not neede much to delate on it, but to ſpeake freelie and compendiouſly vnto you, I holde you to be the moſt venomous ſerpent, that crawleth in a common-wealth, and would aduiſe all men that tender their owne ſafetie to ſhunne you, as an Harpie, and ſtop their eares at your words, as the enchanting of Mermaydes: <hi>Plus nocet lingua adulato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, quam gladius perſecutoris:</hi> your tongue doth more hurt then warre or peſtilence, and you are the cauſer of more miſchiefe, then any impietie whatſoeuer, lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling men in the ſleepe of ſecuritie: whereas, if they were kept waking, and had their faults laid apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before them, no doubt but that either ſhame or feare would worke a reformation in them: guiltie therefore are you of all thoſe crimes, which they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and acceſſarie to their enormities, whom you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and ſooth vp in follies: your fortune therefore will be full foule in the end, &amp; though you may flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for a time, and liue in fauour, yet when your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions are found falſe, your friendſhip fained, your counſell hurtfull vnto them, then you may giue an
<pb facs="tcp:20674:19"/> 
                     <hi>vltimum vale</hi> to your happineſſe; they which loued you wil loath you to death, they which credited you, will not beleeue you for a world, though then you ſhould tell them neuer ſo truly: they that graced you, wil be the firſt that ſhal publiſh your diſgrace, &amp; work your ruine: becauſe like a trayterous perſon you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured theirs, by your conceiling their follies, and animating them to any villanie. Away the Paraſite ſneaked, and another knocked at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="wanton wife" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The wanton wife entreth to know her Fortune, whom <hi>Mockso</hi> deſcribeth.</head>
                  <p>WHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi> A ſwéete woman, no doubt anſwered <hi>Mockſo,</hi> doe you not ſmell her? a cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eye, ſhe turneth it with a trice, a faire haire, if it be her owne: an high forehead, if it be not forced: a rare face, if it be not painted: a white necke, if it be not plaſtered: a ſtraight backe, if it be not bolſtered: a ſlender waſt, if it be not pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: a prettie foote, if it be not in ſhooe-makers laſte: a faire and rare creature, if ſhe be not diſhoneſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the wanton wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Si fas dicere,</hi> She came naked into the Cittie, and ſhal ſo returne, vnleſſe ſhe doe penance with a white ſhéete pinned about her, as ſhe now deſerneth her huſband marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her for pure loue, and had nought with her, and ſo hee is likely to haue, ſo long as he hath her: yet ſhee will flaunt it with the fineſt, and gadde abroad with the giddieſt, looking for greater attendance then an Empreſſe, and more duty then a Dutcheſſe, enuying all that are more brauely trapped then her ſelfe, and confederate with few but ſuch as are wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:20674:19"/> intrapped, as ſhe is: no faſhion can be extant, but ſhe muſt haue a fling at it: no ſight to be ſeene, but ſhe muſt view it: not a gewgaw to be heard of, but ſhe muſt haue it; ſhe will buy nothing that is cheape, weare nothing that is common, eate nothing that is not coſtly: her honeſt huſband is her hobie-horſe at home, and abroad her foole; amongſt her copeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, wanton wenches game amongſt themſelues, and wagges ſport to point at with two fingers: who is ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by her, that he were better in his graue: by day he dare not meet her, ſhe is ſo man'd with make-ſhift, by night hee feareth to lie with her, her touch is ſo ambiguous: with meat he cannot pleaſe her, ſhe is ſo dainty, in clothes hee cannot kéepe her, ſhe is ſo coſtly, with words he cannot fit her, ſhee is ſo captious, in deede hee cannot content her, for ſhee is a wanton: If he endeuour with good counſell to diſſwade her, (ſhe ſaith) he preacheth too learnedly for her to edifie, if hee gybe and ieſt at her follie, then he is all wit or a wittall, if he keepeth her ſhort of mony, then ſhe rappeth out an oath, that ſhe will haue coyne though ſhe be hanged for it: if he keepe her cloſe within doores, the next time he ſtirreth out,<note place="margin">Nupta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum timeat, cas ta ſit cuſtodia nuptae.</note> a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant clappeth him on the ſhoulder, for ſome debt ſhee hath entred vnknowne to him, for ſuch a purpoſe: <hi>Tum ſua do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minantur aula, Dulichii Samii<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c.</hi> To be breefe, ſhee is her huſbands affliction, her childrens diſgrace, her friends ſcandall, royſters and rake-hels randeuouce, a wanton wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked well fauoured wife.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his Oration to the wanton wife, detecting the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of her beaſtly life, and Fortune.</head>
                  <p>VVEre your minde as richly beautified as your body, you could not be too highly prized; but ſeeing the beaſtlineſſe of your behauiour, blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth
<pb facs="tcp:20674:20"/> your beautie: I cannot but condemne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne you: who hauing plighted your faith, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly obliged your ſelfe vnto an husband, are now become moſt faithleſſe and perfidious, leauing the fruite which was allottted, you fall to the forbidden tree: which driuing you out of Paradiſe, will expoſe you to the infamie of the world: if you can delude your husbands eyes with demure carriage, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe him with a good conceit thereof, then you care not how you couſen him of his goods priuily, deride him cloſely, abuſe him behinde his backe, ſo all bee done <hi>Caute</hi> it is well done: but if you conſider the cauſe aright, it is your ſelfe you wrong: there is an eie which ſeeth you, though neuer ſo cloſely cabined, there is an eare that heareth you, whiſper you neuer ſo ſoftly: there is an heart which apprehendeth you, contriue you neuer ſo cunningly: from which if you cannot conceale your thoughts, wordes and workes, neuer laugh in your ſleeue, how you haue gulled or bulled your husband: nay many are ſo impudent they care not who know it, they thinke it a credite to bee notorious, an honour to haue Gallants ſeeke vnto them: where carrion is it is no maruell to find Kites: pleaſure hath an amiable face, but a loathſome bodie, a ſweete taſte, but a ſowre digeſtion; a delicious life, but a miſerable death: looke vpon that plot in my Garden, you ſee it freſh and fragrant, if I ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many of my neighbours to fling their Garbidge on it, it would become a fulſome dunghil: or behold my well, the water in it is cleere and ſweete, if the ſinkes here about ſhould haue paſſage to it, they
<pb facs="tcp:20674:20"/> would ſoone alter the cleareneſſe and ſweeteneſſe of the water: ſo now you are ſound and louely to looke on: you may maintaine the ſame for a ſmall ſpace, but being common vlcers, filth and blanches will breed vpon you like frogges and toades in ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pooles:<note place="margin">Dedit hanc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio tabem, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> dabit plures ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut grex totus in aruis, vnius ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie cadit &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine porci una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> contacta liuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ducit ab vna: Iun.</note> And therefore I cannot blame thoſe which are timerous of their wiues, for their owne bodies ſafetie: one rotten ſheepe corrupts a flocke: one meaſeled Hoggeſmites an Heard: one plagued perſon infects a people. Now to your Fortune, If you once looſe your good name, you will neuer recouer it: if now in youth you forſake your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and play falſe, in your age when none reſpect you, he will reiect you: your children may begge or ſteale, wil he toile to maintaine other mens gettings? If he deceaſe before you, no honeſt man will haue you, vnleſſe ſome of your deboſhed companions, more for lucre then for loue, who will neuer truſt you, knowing you falſe to your former husband: and then perchance you would wiſh you had beene more conſtant to your firſt betrothed, and leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident to euery cogging companion: but it will bee then too late, now lament your follie, and beginne a new life, abandon lewde company, and idleneſſe, and you may haue many a faire day, and future felicity: elſe expect nothing but miſerie, ſhame, and many misfortunes in the end, which will fall heauily vpon you, if you doe not now labour to preuent them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſhe walked, and another rapped at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="jealous man" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20674:21"/>
                  <head>The iealous man entereth to know his fortune, <hi>Mockso</hi> deſcribing him.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is that, ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi> One as melancholie as a Cat, anſwered <hi>Mockſo,</hi> and glared vpon me, as if he would haue looked through me: ſure hee lacketh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he gazeth ſo about him: holde not downe thine head for ſhame, like a beaſt: but erect thy countenance, like a man. High-ho how he ſigheth, &amp; beateth his breſt, as if there were ſomething there angering him: Why doth he féele his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ſo often, it is ſmooth enough, he doubteth (I lay my life) they wil ſprowt out ſhortly, and ſhal ſoone become as huge headed as was <hi>Acteon,</hi> after hee gazed on the Goddeſſe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing her ſelfe with her Nymphes in the Fountaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the iealous man.</head>
                  <p>HE is more afraid then hurt (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) hee mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth his minde without cauſe, and troubleth his thoughts without true reaſon: his wife is faire, therefore hee thinketh her falſe: of a wittie diſpoſition, therefore hee dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth her a wagge-taile: all that ſpeake to her, hee thinketh wooe her, &amp; euery man that looketh on her, he iudgeth loues her: let her ſpeake him faire, then ſhe faigneth, let her vſe him dutifully, then ſhe doth counterfet: if ſhe keepeth home, it is <hi>volens nolens</hi> againſt her wil: let her goe abroad, then his head aketh, and his heart panteth: is ſhee neatly arraied, that is but to allure and pleaſe others: is ſhe homely dreſſed, ſhe knoweth he wil kéepe houſe that day: goe they in the ſtréetes together, if ſhe glanceth but a ſide, hee knoweth her minde forſooth: courteſie in her, is the loadſtone of her luſt: and affabilitie the cunning Orator for her concupiſcence: bringeth he any to his table, if ſhe carue them, it is in hope
<pb facs="tcp:20674:21"/> of ſome amorous requitall: if ſhee drinke to them, their pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings are but as pledges of their concealed loues: they which proffer him kindneſſe, he ſurmiſeth it pretended for opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to his wife: and they which frequent his houſe, be they of his néereſt alliance or kindred, he ſuſpecteth: to be briefe with him, ſhe is his fortunes fore-ſtaller, his mindes miſerie, his bodies bane, a reiecter of his moſt intimate familiers, a ſuſpitious ill liuer (for the wife would neuer haue ſought her daughter in the Ouen, vnleſſe ſhe her ſelfe had beene there in former times) an erronious hereticke in the opinion of his wife, an vnreaſonable and cauſeleſſe iealous man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>The Fortune-tellers Oration to the iealous man, declaring his folly and fortune.</head>
                  <p>SIr, of all men, I holde you moſt ſenſeleſſe, who without certaine grownd and ſure experience ſhould miſconceit, that which was neuer meant you: cannot your wife be faire, but laſciuious? what ſay you to <hi>Lucretia?</hi> can you not be abſent? but ſhe will play foule? how thinke you of <hi>Penelope?</hi> who in the tenne yeares abſence of her husband, lined chaſte and vntouched: but ſuppoſe that which you ſuſpect, were certaine: ſores paſt cure are paſt care: <hi>Quod factum est, infectum eſſe nequit:</hi> that which is done cannot be vndone: that which will be ſhall be: if ſhe be chaſte and vertuous, no beautie can tempt her, no gifts allure her, no perſwaſions winne her: but if ſhe be diſloyall, keepe her neuer ſo cloſe, ſhee will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other flie out in deſpight of you.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20674:22"/>
                     <l>Vt iam ſeruaris bene corpus adultera mens est</l>
                     <l>Nec custodiri, ni velit ipſa potest.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Centum fronte oculos centum Ceruice gerebat: Argus &amp; hos v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſaepe fefellit amor. Ouid.</note>When <hi>Iupiter</hi> loued <hi>Io,</hi> a delicious Damſell, his wife being miſtruſtfull, dogged him, to finde out his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: who to conceale his fault, turned the Lady into an Haifer, which <hi>Iuno</hi> begged, and reſigned to the cuſtodie of <hi>Argus,</hi> who although he was faigned to haue an hundred eies: yet was he beguiled of the ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well he watched ſo narrowly: ſo be you neuer ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant and circumſpect, if ſhe be ſo diſpoſed, ſhe will, <hi>Non caret effectu quod voluere duo:</hi> needleſſe therfore will your care be if you haue no cauſe: and although you haue good reaſon of none effect, <hi>Naturam expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las furca, licet vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> recurret:</hi> Now to your fortune: if you be obſtinate in your beleefe, and ſo confirme in your falſe faith, you will martir your ſelfe moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, your body will be ſoone waſted, and your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance conſumed, becauſe when your thoughts are deſtracted with ſuch friuolous matters, you can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeriouſly negociate your eſtate-concerning, and ſupporting deſignes, your beſt way therefore, is to thinke the beſt, iudge the beſt, <hi>et modo te ſanum fingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſanus eris:</hi> away the iealous man departed, and an other knocked at the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="lover" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Louer entering to know his fortune, <hi>Mockso</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth him.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is that ſaid <hi>Fido?</hi> I know not, ſaid <hi>Mockſo,</hi> but he looketh very pittifully vpon it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:20674:22"/> ſadly in: a finicall fellow he is, and very faſhionable, a ſtiffe necke he hath, which God hateth, and a ſtreight dublet, which no drunkard could endure: for if he had it but one ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he would not leaue it worth a button, ſure his taylor hath not done well to make it ſo ſhort waſted: crie him mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie now I looke ſo low, he hath put all the waſte in the knées of his breeches, currage man: if ſhe will not, another will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Louer.</head>
                  <p>AS ſimple as he ſtandeth there (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) hee hath let his owne arme blood himſelfe in ſtead of a Barber-Surgeon, and quaffed an health thereof in praiſe of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe when he had done: hee hath kneeled oftner in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his ſweete heart then his Sauiour: hee cruciateth himſelf with thought of her, and wearieth al his friends with talking on her, he is trapt in ſo long contemplation of her heauenly by him ſurmiſed beautie, that ſome times miſſing his appointed meales, <hi>Oſcula dat ligno,</hi> he kiſſeth the poſt, moſt daintie face, ſuppoſing it his loue, and imbraceth his pillow or the ayre in his armes circumference, her bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely imagined preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he maketh her a Dietie with his adoration, and extolleth the luſtre of her eyes aboue the Sun and Moone: he is eliuated into the third heauen when hee dreameth of her, and will admit no ſublunarie reſemblances in his compariſons concerning her: though ſhe haue a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes head, a Virginian noſe, a Spaniſh face, a Flemiſh necke and a Turkiſh ſtature: all the morning he waſteth in finifying his body to pleaſe her eye, all the afternoone he cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out choice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>remeditate ſpeeches to delight her eare, all ſupper while (if they table together) he peereth and prieth into the platters to picke out dainty morſels, to content her maw, and almoſt all the night he watcheth and prayeth for her, ſighing like a ſenceleſſe beaſt, and ſobbing like a filly ſot, if he be riuald and put beſides her: to be briefe, hee is his
<pb facs="tcp:20674:23"/> friends pittie, his enemies deriſion, his ſoules ſorrow, his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies decay, and his ſweet-hearts deriſion: A forſaken louer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fido</hi> his Oration to the Louer, reuealing his fondnes and fortune.</head>
                  <p>BY this it ſeemeth you are in loue, with whom? a woman: good, what woman? beauteous, rich, or honourable? ſo, how doth ſhe requite your loue? with ſcorn, hate, deriſion: ſhe is a woman, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to man, as one defineth: the greateſt pleaſure that can betide a man, when he is depriued of her: witnes <hi>Galba,</hi> who ſeeing his neighbours wife hang her ſelfe vpon a figge tree, deſired a ſlippe thereof to graft, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it would beare more ſuch fruite, meaning his wife: The toylſomeſt burden that combreth a man, as he certified, who when the reſt of his companie caſt ouer-bord ſuch ſtuffe as was moſt cumberſome vnto them (being ſo commaunded by the Maſter of the Shippe) tooke his wife in his arms, with intent to fling her into the Sea, had hee not beene interupted. If then a wife be the contrary to an husband, what concord can there be betweene them? if a pleaſure to be loſt, who would ſigh to be depriued of one? if a burden and clogge to be kept, who would not skipp for ioy to haue his clogge taken from him? But ſhe is beauteous, rich, or honourable; what is beautie with vntoward conditions, but a faire flower with an ill ſauour, a painted ſepulchre fil'd with putrid bones? what are riches with wayward qualities, but golden
<pb facs="tcp:20674:23"/> Mazers fraught with deadly poyſon? And as the Cynick likened a rich man without knowledge, to a ſheepe with a golden fleece: ſo you may reſemble a wealthy woman with wilfull manners, to a Iade with golden trappings: and what is honour? a celeſtiall thing, a radiant ſtarre (you will ſay) but thoſe ſtarrs are not all one ſome are <hi>fixae,</hi> ſome <hi>errantes,</hi> ſome <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes:</hi> that is, ſome are fixed, ſome wandring, ſome falling ſtarres: but ſhe you admired, was none of the fixed, as her wandring and falling from you, ſheweth: beſides ſhe ſcorneth, hateth and derideth you: if any of your beſt friends ſhould ſerue you ſo, you would renounce them, yet you will reuerence her, your worſt enemie: but men of your mould are like Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels, which will creepe neereſt to them that cudgell them; ſo the frowarder their ſweete hearts are, the forwarder are they to crouch vnto them: <hi>Quod licet ingratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod non licet acrius vrit,</hi> whereas being leſſe obſequious they might fare better, <hi>noui mulierum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, vbi velis nolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; vbi nolis cupiunt vltro.</hi> Some reaſon had <hi>Cenſorius Cato</hi> to leaue this precept, for future times, Truſt not a woman: the dogged Philoſopher knew cauſes enough, when he ſaid it was too late for the olde man, and too ſoone for the young to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Yet I ſpeake not this in diſgrace of vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or to deterre you from marriage: but for a man the King &amp; commander of al earthly crea ures, whoſe body is pure, whoſe minde more magnanimious, to be deiected in ſpirit, pale in phyſnomy, leane in his limmes, and all for a woman: nay for ſuch a woman as doth ſcorne, hate, and deride him: fie it is intoller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.
<pb facs="tcp:20674:24"/> Were ſhe true and faithfull vnto you, in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and honeſt ſort, I would kindle and combine you with the beſt counſell I could: but being otherwiſe, take theſe precepts, which if you follow, will allay all luſt and loue in you: The firſt is, to abandon idleneſſe, the nurſe of wantonnes: The ſecond, ſhunne ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bee eyther doing ſomething, or diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and paſſing the time away in company: The third, to haue a good conceit of your ſelfe, to cheere vp your ſpirits, and doubt not, but to haue her bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: The fourth is, to mince and extenuate any lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable part in her, but to diſplay and augment whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer deformity you know by her: for loue is feigned blinde, becauſe he cannot iudge aright, but maketh a mountaine of a Mole-hill, a Saint of a Sow: the beſt courſe therefore to baniſh him, is, to contrarie him in all his aſſeuerations, to priſe at a low rate, that he highly vallueth: as for inſtance, Is the partie fatte? fatte meate will cloy any man: Is ſhe leane? what good ſtomacke careth for bones? if ſhe be pale of complexion, ſhe will proue but a puler: is ſhe high coloured? an ill cognizance: is ſhe ſilent? the ſtill Sow will eate vp all the draugh: dooth ſhee talke much? a pratling goſſip ſhe is likely to proue, and who would be troubled with a tatling tongue, and ſuch like? Fiftly, if ſhee vſeth you hardly either in words or deeds, or countenanceth any of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies or euill willers, ſet it downe in your Table-bookes, and write it vpon the wal in your bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that you may at al times better remember them: &amp; conſider, if ſhe tendered you, ſhe wold not wrong
<pb facs="tcp:20674:24"/> you: Many more could I expreſſe, but I ſhould be ouer-tedious: therefore to your fortune, which now is bad enough, neither would I wiſh any worſe, though I ſhould wiſh them hanged, for hanging is the end of care, but loue the enterance: but what will be hereafter, that is as your choiſe is: if you be aduiſed, hope the beſt, if not, looke for crooked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, as well as ſome of your betters haue had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you: away the Louer walked, and another came to the gate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="virgin" type="part">
               <div type="description">
                  <head>The Virgin entereth to know her fortune, <hi>Mockso</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing her.</head>
                  <p>VVHo is it ſaid <hi>Fido? Diana</hi> or one of her darlings, he replied, I am perplexed with her proportion, the very glimſe of her, hath amazed me: beauty ſitteth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thronized on herbrowes, modeſty in her eies, health in her chéekes, ſilence on her tongue, Balſamum in her breath, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculation on her necke, temperance on her waſte, comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on her whole body: <hi>Cytherea</hi> may ſigh at her portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Delia</hi> bluſh at her behauiour: her lookes turne not too and fro, her ſpéech is not obſtreperous, no pride in her appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, no affectation in her gate: the map of modeſtie, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of pureneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="opinion">
                  <head>Opinion of the Virgin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REmtenes</hi> (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) now you haue layed giving aſide, you haue eaſed me of a labour, a pur-blinde wit may perceiue what ſhe is: an immaculate virgin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="fortune">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20674:25"/>
                  <head>The Fortune-tellers Oration to the Virgine, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her to chastitie, and ſhewing her fortune.</head>
                  <p>AMiable Maid, which hitherto haſt led a chaſt and vnpolluted life,<note place="margin">Non eſt digna ponderatio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentis animae.</note> perſeuer ſtill as you haue begun, and make no doubt but to be right happy, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with ſo vneſtimable a iewell as chaſtitie: which is a caeleſtiall beatitude, the ſiſter of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the conquereſſe of concupiſcence, the Queene of vertues, although it vouchſafeth to inhabite the minde and body of you an earthly creature: ſeeing therefore it is ſuch an ineſtimable iewell, how warily are you to keepe it? ſuch a Peereleſſe Princeſſe, how loyally are you to loue it?<note place="margin">Maior victoria virginum quam angelorum.</note> ſuch a victorious trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, how carefully are you to guard it? ſo vnmatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably allied, how much are you to make of it? All which that you may the better effect,<note place="margin">He giueth her a Lilly the Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliphick of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie.</note> I will beſtowe this flower vpon you: it is a Lilly not naturall, but artificially compoſed like to a naturall Lilly, hauing ſixe ſiluer leaues, containing ſixe ſeuerall poſies, to preſerue your chaſtitie: the firſt whereof hath this poſie engrauen in it: <hi>Cibi &amp; potus ſobrietas:</hi> that is, temperance in eating and drinking, which is an effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe to quell &amp; conquer wantonneſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as exceſſe of both, or either of them, doth animate and make it rebellious, and alſo disfigure the party pleaſed with the ſame: for immoderate eating bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fiue blemiſhes in the behauiour of a virgine, which do deforme her reputation, more then fifteene
<pb facs="tcp:20674:25"/> wheales or pimples would diſgrace her face: The firſt is ſcurrility of ſpeech, a naughtie thing in any; The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, talkatiueneſſe or much babling: The third, a fooliſh ioy or petulant kinde of geſture: The fourth, vomiting, belching, or ſuch like: The fift, drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of body and dulneſſe of minde: which although they are ſlightly obſerued in others: yet are they ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner marked in a maiden: as blacke ſpots eaſier eſpied in a white cloath, then in darke coloured veſtures: touching inordinate drinking of wine, all are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it, but you eſpecially of all others, <hi>Virgo fugiat vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vt venenum: nam vinum in adoleſcentia est du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex incendium voluptatis:</hi> that is, a virgine ought to reiect wine, as poiſon, which is a two-fold fire-brand to kindle luſt in youth:<note place="margin">Sine Cerere &amp; Baccho friget Venus.</note> abſtinence therefore is the firſt weapon to defend chaſtitie, and put the enemie to flight: which as it is comely in any preſence, ſo it is commodious for any feminine perſonage: kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them from foggineſſe, groſneſſe and fiery faces: <hi>Deducunt cibum, tametſi eſt bona natura vt reddant cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura iunceas,</hi> that is, as one ſaid of Virgins in his time, they pinch their bellies of meate (a good cuſtome) that they might be as ſmall as bull-ruſhes. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond leafe of this Lilly hath engrauen in it <hi>Aſperitas vestitus,</hi> that is, courſeneſſe and plaineneſſe of appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: for gariſh and fantaſticall cloathes, are ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reporters of wanton mindes, therefore ſaid one which had ſome trafique with ſuch light ſtuffe:<note place="margin">Veſtitus in ſiguis &amp; mollis ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biae vexillum, niduſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> luxurie.</note> that ſumptuous and ſoft raiments were the Enſignes of pride: but light and looſe cloathing the index of lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urie: and as in olde time ſuch as ſolde horſes, were
<pb facs="tcp:20674:26"/> wont to put flowers or boughes vpon their heads, to reueale that they were vendible: ſo, ſuch as trim and trick themſelues with toyes &amp; gewgawes, ſhew that they are willing, if any will: let therefore your appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell be plaine, yet comely, which will ſtop the mouth of euill report: and as courſe as you can indure it, if you meane to tame your luſt.<note place="margin">Otia ſi tollas pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere Cupidinis arcus. Ouid.</note> The third leafe is ſet downe <hi>laboris ſtrenuitas:</hi> labour and exerciſe, for if your minde be buſied about any good huſwifrie, or ſetled ſeriouſly vpon any honeſt exerciſe, luſt can haue no power ouer you, therefore wee reade how <hi>Penelope,</hi> a conſtant Lady, would carde and to aſe wooll her ſelfe, leaſt ſhee ſhould be idle, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſubiect to laſciuious thoughts and deedes, in the tenne yeeres abſence of her husband: and the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtals if at any time they had let the fire on the Altar goe out, they were enioyned to kindle it againe with the beames of the ſunne. In the fourth leafe, is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Custodia ſenſuum:</hi> that is, not to giue your ſenſes any ſcope or liberty,<note place="margin">Vitijs in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum per oculos eſt via.</note> eſpecially the ſight, or hearing, for iniquitie through the eye-lids glideth into the heart: and many haue beene entrapped by giuing audience to the alluring ſongs of the Sirens. In the fift leafe, <hi>modestia verborum,</hi> modeſt words you muſt vſe, <hi>qualis homo, talis oratio,</hi> ſuch as the woman is ſuch are her words, for a proud woman will be rapping arrogant words, a fooliſh woman fond words, a wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton woman laſciuious words, but a chaſt woman modeſt words and few: Therfore ſaid a graue Father, that the ſpeech of a virgine ought to be wiſe, ciuill, ſlow and ſparing: that ſhe might be accounted as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb facs="tcp:20674:26"/> for her ſpeech, as for her chaſtity: for euill words corrupt good manners. In the ſixt and laſt leafe of this Lilly, is written, <hi>Fuga opportunitatum,</hi> the eſchuing of opportunity, to ſhunn the company and conuerſation of men: for, albeit I am a man my ſelfe, and ſhall be reputed fooliſh to bewray mine owne neaſt, yet to benefit ſuch a goodly creature as your ſelfe, whom it were villany to iniurie, I will diſplay the practiſes of ſome, though all vſe not the ſame, that you may take heede of any, that would goe about to rifle you of your deereſt iewel, without law or hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, I meane mariage. Men generally are wiſer then women in goodneſſe, yet are they ſillier in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and contriuing deceit, then craftie and ſenſuall women: and as they are more ſimple then craftie women: ſo are they ſubtiller then well minded may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, who as they are guiltleſſe of effecting deceipt: ſo are they innocent of ſuſpecting deceipt.</p>
                  <p>It is no glory (I confeſſe) to deceiue a woman, no point of valour to ouerthrow the weaker veſſell, yet if this weaker veſſell be artificially garniſhed, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally beautified, what labour will they not take to attaine it? what watching will they omit to ſteale it? what wealth will they ſpare for to compaſſe it? and when they haue gotten it into their cuſtody, how do ſome of them eſteeme it? euen as children gewgaws, to dandle and play with it a while: but as ſoone as they eye a new deuiſe, they caſt away the olde, and neuer are in quiet, till they be fingering the newe, or as Warriours of olde time, which did ſpend much coſt and paines to ſubdue a Citie, and when they had
<pb facs="tcp:20674:27"/> brought it into ſubiection, rifled it and ranſackt it; marched to another, and ſo to a third, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>There was a pure virgine (as I heard) dwelling not farre from me, who had ſo firmely deuoted her ſelfe to chaſtity, that the Inhabitants thereabout did admire her; till a luſtie gallant, rich and well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned wooed her, who neuer left battering the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke of her heart with piercing oathes, vowes and proteſtations, darted from his ſmooth tongue, till he had almoſt brought her to the bay: within a while after ſhe had conſidered his actions, how hee would teare his haire, weepe in moſt ſeeming ſadneſſe, kiſſe her hand with feare and trembling, and proffer vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted many ſeruile ceremonies, fearing her ſelfe to breake an oath or violate a vow, truſted that hee had the ſame feare in him, which he had not, condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his deſire; which ſo ſoone as hee had accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, forſooke her vtterly: after him another came vnto her, and ſerued her with the ſame ſawce: then a third: at laſt, ſhe began to wax warie: a fourth came vnto her, whoſe faſhion was to try all, and if they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, left them incontinently, but hee laboured in vaine, for his gifts could preuaile nothing, nor his promiſes perſwade her (ſhee had faire warning one would thinke): to be briefe, he liked, loued and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her, and the ſecond night as they lay together, the good man ſaid to her, Thou knoweſt ſweet heart how often I tempted thee, and I proteſt, if thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt conſented, I had forſaken thee vtterly: tut, tut husband, ſaid ſhee, (ſure ſhee was halfe a ſleepe, and halfe waking) I trow I was a little wiſer then ſo, for
<pb facs="tcp:20674:27"/> three had ſerued me in the like ſort, before euer I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eld your face. This I do not relate, that you ſhould make the ſame experiment, but that you might auoid the like men, for he that maketh no ſcruple to breake the ſeuenth commandement, will make as little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to keepe the third: beſides, if he ſhould keepe his promiſe, he would haue you alwaies in iealouſie: for if you feare not to diſpleaſe God, before you are married (who forbiddeth fornication) will not your husband be perſwaded, that you will haue as little feare to commit adulterie, when you are eſpouſed? take this Lilly, and think vpon euery word and poſie engrauen in it: and aboue all, beleeue not words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting any diſhoneſt requeſt. I haue a picture here to the ſame purpoſe: looke vpon this Lady, it was <hi>Dido</hi> Queene of Carthage, who being too credulous in beleeuing a wandering Prince, fell to folly with him, and after forſaken, cauſed a great fire to be made, and for griefe and anguiſh leaped into it: this other is <hi>Phillis</hi> Queene of <hi>Rodope,</hi> a virgin, before ſhe lent an attentiue eare to <hi>Demophoon,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of royall race, who after he had gotten his purpoſe, neuer returned neere her againe, ſo that for ſhame and auoiding future ſorrow, ſhe hung her ſelfe, as this picture liuely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth: take it with you, and think that if theſe two beauteous Queenes were deceaued, it were an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard for to truſt, <hi>Fide, ſed cui vide:</hi> it is an old ſaying, trie before you truſt: but if Maydens follow that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they may be truſt round before, and after ſerued as theſe were. Away the Virgine walked, like <hi>Iuno</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20674:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the Empire, and others were at the gate e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting entrance, but <hi>Fido</hi> beeing weake and wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſmiſſed them, till ſome other time, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with committed his ſelfe to his Cloſet.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20674:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
